<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2022-08-29T11:05:14+00:00</updated><id>https://mefelixahe.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>This is my personal blog! </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Adding Math to my jekyll webpage</title><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/adding-math/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Adding Math to my jekyll webpage"/><published>2022-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/adding-math</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/adding-math/"><![CDATA[<p>By default it was not possible to use math equations in the markdown Jekyll blogs. I was using github readme markdown earlier and there it supports the typical Latex math text.</p> <p>So to solve any problem in my life, I google and found the solution right away. Thanks to this person’s comment <a href="https://github.com/mmistakes/minimal-mistakes/issues/735#issuecomment-269500816">here</a> and this blog <a href="https://www.katarinahoeger.com/2017/12/08/jekyll-supports-math">here</a>. Both essentially say the same thing.</p> <p>Add a directory called</p> <pre><code class="language-cmd">"_includes\scripts.html"
</code></pre> <p>Edit the html with</p> <div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="nt">&lt;script </span><span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">"text/javascript"</span> <span class="na">async</span>
  <span class="na">src=</span><span class="s">"https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-MML-AM_CHTML"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/script&gt;</span>

</code></pre></div></div> <p>This would allow you to use mathjax library to write equations. You just have to had the following in the YAML</p> <div class="language-md highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nn">---</span>
<span class="na">mathjax</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="no">true</span>
<span class="nn">---</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Fun fact:</p> <blockquote> <p>YAML stands for <strong>yet another markup language</strong> or YAML ain’t markup language (a recursive acronym)</p> <p>YAML stuff is on the top of every markdown files adding data</p> </blockquote> <p>My first attempt to write equations</p> <pre><code class="language-math">$$ a = 1 $$
$$ b = 2 $$
$$ a + b = 3 $$
</code></pre> <p>\(a = 1\) \(b = 2\) \(a + b = 3\)</p> <p>It works great. I will use the following webpage as Mathjax reference:</p> <ul> <li> <p><a href="https://math.meta.stackexchange.com/questions/5020/mathjax-basic-tutorial-and-quick-reference/5024#5024">MathJax basic tutorial and quick reference - Mathematics Meta Stack Exchange</a></p> </li> <li> <p><a href="https://jojozhuang.github.io/tutorial/mathjax-cheat-sheet-for-mathematical-notation/">MathJax Cheat Sheet for Mathematical Notation @ https://jojozhuang.github.io</a></p> </li> </ul> <p>It was little scary for me as a new user to jekyll to add an extra directory like include and scripts.html. Because in past, every time I add something like this the whole site stops functioning properly. I am glad that it worked properly and in the future I might be able to add more scripts like this.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nimesh Chahare</name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="coding"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By default it was not possible to use math equations in the markdown Jekyll blogs. I was using github readme markdown earlier and there it supports the typical Latex math text.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Problems encountered with Jekyll</title><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/jekyll-problems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Problems encountered with Jekyll"/><published>2022-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/jekyll-problems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/jekyll-problems/"><![CDATA[<p>All I wanted is to have a website with simple navigation bar pointing to my blog, my CV, and my publications. I used jekyll and minimal mistakes theme to make the webpage. Earlier everything was well with the webpage.</p> <h2 id="navigation-bar-and-hamburger-menu">Navigation bar and Hamburger menu</h2> <p>I added an extra section in the navigation called media. With this the bar became more crowded and there was no more space to accommodate all options. The hamburger menu appeared automatically. Amazing right? No. When I changed the order of the pages, it stopped working and now the hamburger menu has been disabled. Even though I have changed nothing. The options were going into the Home button and disappearing. I had to change the name of sections so that they can fit in mobile devices.</p> <p>Online people were saying that this is the problem of jekyll not the theme.</p> <h2 id="follow-menu">Follow menu</h2> <p>This is when I realize somethings up with the follow button which appears after resizing the screen or in mobile. Yesterday it worked perfectly. Today it has stopped.</p> <p>Again, jekyll is blamed for this. I am too clueless to solve this problem.</p> <p>Only solution I see is to retry building the website and hope it works.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nimesh Chahare</name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="coding"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[All I wanted is to have a website with simple navigation bar pointing to my blog, my CV, and my publications. I used jekyll and minimal mistakes theme to make the webpage. Earlier everything was well with the webpage.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making a webpage using Jekyll</title><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/learning-jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making a webpage using Jekyll"/><published>2022-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/learning-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/learning-jekyll/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the best things I found on the internet. Basically I was browsing my twitter feed and some random person said “you need to have a personal website. Use this webinar to make it with jekyll.” At this point of time I already had this webpage with my CV. But I realized that I can’t really have nice things like navigation bar or side bar or any other bar in my website.</p> <p>I even had hard time putting the images in. This was all because my reluctance to install jekyll and rubygems on my computer. I was using github site directly in my browser. So I took a look at this <a href="https://youtu.be/7SBXl94xNl8">video</a>. It finally looked easy and doable. So I decided to give it another shot.</p> <p>I used the following commands:</p> <p>First download ruby+devkit from <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/installation/windows/">here</a>. Follow the instructions.</p> <pre><code class="language-cmd">ruby -v

gem install bundler
gem install jekyll


jekyll -v
</code></pre> <p>Then make a directory and open “Mingw64” github stuff.</p> <pre><code class="language-cmd">jekyll new myblog
cd myblog

bundle install
bundle exec jekyll serve
</code></pre> <p>Last two commands will be used all the time.</p> <p>I was able to edit and make pages all along by following these links:</p> <p>GitHub repo: <a href="https://github.com/laurburke2/laurburke2.github.io">https://github.com/laurburke2/laurbur…</a>)</p> <p>Finally following are the commands for the git.</p> <pre><code class="language-git">git remote add origin
https://&lt;PERSONAL_ACCESS_TOKEN&gt;@github.com/&lt;username&gt;/&lt;username&gt;.github.io.git

git add .
git commit -m "Initial Commit"
git remote -v
git push origin master
</code></pre> <p>My final webpage looks like <a href="nchahare.github.io">this</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Nimesh Chahare</name></author><category term="jekyll"/><category term="coding"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the best things I found on the internet. Basically I was browsing my twitter feed and some random person said “you need to have a personal website. Use this webinar to make it with jekyll.” At this point of time I already had this webpage with my CV. But I realized that I can’t really have nice things like navigation bar or side bar or any other bar in my website.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On technique and science. J D Bernal</title><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/jdbernal1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On technique and science. J D Bernal"/><published>2022-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/jdbernal1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/jdbernal1/"><![CDATA[<p>“Technique is an individually acquired and socially secured way of doing something; a science is a way of understanding how to do it in order to do it better.”</p> <p>J.D. Bernal, Science in History: Volume 1: The Emergence of Science</p>]]></content><author><name>Nimesh Chahare</name></author><category term="quotations"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Technique is an individually acquired and socially secured way of doing something; a science is a way of understanding how to do it in order to do it better.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mechanics of epithelial layers subjected to controlled pressure and tension</title><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/phd-project/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mechanics of epithelial layers subjected to controlled pressure and tension"/><published>2022-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/phd-project</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/phd-project/"><![CDATA[<p>This is my main PhD project. I started with Prof. Xavier Trepat, an experimentalist, and Prof. Marino Arroyo, a mathematician. I chose to work with these people to combine my desire to work at the interface of experimentation and theory. I am trained in mechanics of materials; and the materials like Epithelial sheets fascinated me endlessly.</p> <p>These sheets form specialized 3D structures suited to their physiological roles, such as branched alveoli in the lungs, tubes in the kidney, and villi in the intestine. To generate and maintain these structures, epithelia must undergo complex 3D deformations across length and time scales.</p> <p>The mechanics of the epithelial shape remains poorly understood. We already know that the cytoskeleton remodeling and cellular rearrangements make epithelia an active material. However, how these active properties affect shape is not known.</p> <p>To address this question, here we decided to build three dimensional epithelial tissues from scratch. So that we can learn the mechanics of tissues by building. Most of my PhD was to develop a microfluidic setup to engineer 3D epithelial tissues with controlled shape and pressure. It was very hard. I couldnt do it without support of my lab mates: Tom Golde and Thomas Wilson. The outcome was very satisfying and also I got to name the device. I call the device, MOLI: short for Monolayer Inflator.</p> <p>In simple words, with using micropatterning and hydrostatic pressure, I could inflate 2D epithelial monolayer into a 3D epithelial balloon. And the shape of the balloon depends on the pattern. Circular patterns produced an spherical cap or a dome. This simple shape allows us to calculate epithelial tension as a product of pressure applied and half of the dome’s radius of curvature using Laplace’s law.</p> <p>Through this approach, we subject MDCK epithelial cells to a range of lumen pressures at different rates and hence probe the relation between strain and tension Slow pressure changes relative to the time-scales of actin dynamics allow the tissue to accommodate large strain variations. However, under sudden pressure reductions, the tissue develops buckling patterns and folds with different degrees of symmetry-breaking to store excess tissue area. It buckles at multiple levels, going from tissue level to cell level, and looking closely we found it to be buckling at cortex level.</p> <p>I was able to use experiments and mechanical reasoning to rationally direct spontaneous pattern formation, and hence engineer tissue folding.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nimesh Chahare</name></author><category term="work"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Description of my PhD project]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interview by Mechano-control about MISTI</title><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/mechanocontrol-interview/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview by Mechano-control about MISTI"/><published>2022-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/mechanocontrol-interview</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/mechanocontrol-interview/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="article"/><category term="work"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mechanocontrol people interviewed me about my side project of MISTI.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lion in a box</title><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/lion-in-box/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lion in a box"/><published>2022-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/lion-in-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/lion-in-box/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/51962204/183978143-0b1215e5-50ad-4cd9-8366-81c683bcae4f.jpg" alt="lions"/></p> <p>Source: Robert Lang</p>]]></content><author><name>Nimesh Chahare</name></author><category term="origami"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Origami frame with birds and boats</title><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/origami-frame/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Origami frame with birds and boats"/><published>2022-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/origami-frame</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2022/origami-frame/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/51962204/183974839-280fda72-cb92-44dd-8846-b0fa3269c527.jpg" alt="origami_frame"/></p>]]></content><author><name>Nimesh Chahare</name></author><category term="origami"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Me at the origami museum</title><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2021/me-crumpling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Me at the origami museum"/><published>2021-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2021/me-crumpling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2021/me-crumpling/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/51962204/183978455-4db2ff63-a412-48b9-9f26-c675a3182fa1.jpg" alt="meatmuseum"/></p> <p>Source: Crumplings by Vincent Folderer</p>]]></content><author><name>Nimesh Chahare</name></author><category term="origami"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Computational tool for analysing nuclear to cytoplasmic transport</title><link href="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2021/nuclear-transport/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Computational tool for analysing nuclear to cytoplasmic transport"/><published>2021-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-09-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2021/nuclear-transport</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mefelixahe.github.io/blog/2021/nuclear-transport/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Incomplete</strong></p> <p>One day my friend Ion Andreu asked me to collaborate on a new project involving FLIP. I immediately said yes. To be honest, that time was not the best time for me with my main project. I was glad to help. At the time, Ion was working with Ignasi Granero-Moya at Prof. Pere Roca-Cusachs’ lab.</p> <p>Their lab also does mechanobiology but at much more molecular scale than I work in. As we know, cells sense their environment to perform physiological functions. Ion was working on understanding how the sensing happens. Mechanical force is one of the most important elements that make up the cell environment. So Ignasi and Ion were focusing their efforts on exploring the process of cell sensing the external forces.</p> <p>They already had seen that the forces lead nuclear translocation of proteins, where some proteins would go from cytoplasm to nucleus or other way around. However, it was not clear if force controls the nucleocytoplasmic transport. There were many questions to answer, like</p> <ul> <li>Is the transport active or passive?</li> <li>Why is there transport?</li> <li>What happens to the permeability of the nucleus?</li> <li>What is up with the nuclear pore complexes</li> </ul> <p>Ion and Ignasi thought that this transport has to be mechanosensitive, independently of any specific signaling pathway. This would enable a general mechanism by which nuclear force could control the nuclear localization of proteins, and thereby transcription.</p> <p>This is all cool, but where do I come in? Ignasi and Ion decided to look at transport of artificial molecules. They decided to look methods to quantify the transport. Bleaching techniques are an amazing way to quantify movement of molecules. Photobleaching burns the fluorescence of molecule at one particular location. If right after the bleaching, there are other molecules are moving in that location the fluorescence will be recovered. If it doesn’t recover totally, it means that the molecules are bound and not mobile. This technique is called fluorescence recovery after photobleaching (FRAP). This is more standard technique, information you get is how fast the molecules diffuse and how much is the mobile fraction. For me the computation was simple. One script could do all the job: from analysing the images from microscope to the mobile fraction.</p> <p>Using my code, they were able to show that the artificial constructs are totally mobile and do not bind to anything the cells.</p> <p>My proper work came for working with fluorescence loss in photobleaching (FLIP). Here, on contrary to FRAP, you continue to bleach all the time in a small location. If there are mobile molecules, they will get bleached when they come to that location. And the whole cell will be bleached. If all the molecules are immobile then only the bleaching part gets bleached. This method is little complicated to analyse. There is no one single method which people use. There are people who do intense computational models to get the results. There are people who do not so much, which honestly feels wrong.</p> <p>This is where my work started. Luckily I could refer to this paper:</p> <p>Ege, N. et al. Quantitative analysis reveals that actin and src-family kinases regulate nuclear YAP1 and its export. Cell Syst. 6, 692–708.e13 (2018)</p> <p>These people did too much. For me and Ion, it was very clear that we don’t want to do that much.</p> <p>I took it as inspiration and tried to simplify this transport problem. I thought of nucleus and cytoplasm as tanks connected to each other via tubes. But cytoplasm has a leak, implying constant bleaching. Intuitively, it is very clear that the cytoplasm tank is draining and as it is connected to the nucleus tank. Nucleus tank is also draining. The transport across the nucleus can be easily written in the form of simple ordinary differential equations.</p> <p>There was some trouble with this kind of thinking that we forget what fluorescence means. Is it concentration of molecules or number of the molecules. Because of this we had to correct for the volumes of nucleus and cytoplasm.</p> <p>However, in the end it worked great. We could understand the complex behaviour of the nucleus and mechanical forces.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nimesh Chahare</name></author><category term="work"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Description of my collaboration with Ion Andreu]]></summary></entry></feed>